Good morning.
Morning.
Hi.
2.
What kind of music you like playing, John?
I play a little bit of everything.
I I play some classical music sometimes
and some I like like like classic rock
pieces and and right now I'm learning.
Let's see which unchained melody and
Brandi Carlisle's the the story.
And then if the third one is.
Um.
Right. Hold on.
That's cool. Yeah, I I actually,
I should get back into playing my guitar.
I have several of them.
They just hang on the wall.
They just collect dust. But I like,
I like a little bit of classic rock and.
And then.
Uh,
some Blues and still this will mostly
OK.
play.
So what was I? Here we go.
Put a little love in your heart,
Jackie De Shannon.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
OK. Good morning, everyone.
So today we're going to start into the
brownfield portion of the course, so our.
Agenda for that today is that we're going
to be first starting off with
understanding of brownfield and Evergreen
code.
So I got a couple of slides just to bring
us up to speed on that.
Some essential safety measures when we
start to actually modify brownfield.
Code and then then we'll get into
managing a copilot,
some advanced context techniques,
then adding AI guide roles to our project
to make sure that AI is focused on.
The things that are important to the
project,
some documentation and code analysis work
to do a to basically try to help us
understand existing code bases.
Then we'll talk about using that to build
a backlog.
Of changes that we want to make to move
our code base closer to Evergreen.
So building some safety Nets to protect
us as we're generating our modifications
to the legacy code base.
Some test automation and code quality
work that we can do building robust
testing frameworks,
safe brownfield code modifications,
conformance and gap analysis.
And then we'll then we'll finish up with
addressing some technical debt and multi
model implementation comparison exercises.
But before we get into that,
I wanted to just to follow up on some of
the work that we did yesterday.
I bring up our.
Our project.
I spent some time just since we didn't
get as far into that as I would have
liked. I spent some time working on it.
I've added some additional features to
the calculator app and so.
So let's take a quick look at that.
And it was basically using the same
strategy that we're using yesterday.
We're just providing prompts and asking
AI to go ahead and implement those
features.
So you can see here that the the
calculator looks much more like the
standard calculator that comes with
Windows and the reason that that.
Is is I actually took a screenshot of the
calculator in Windows and I gave it to AI
and I said make the calculator look like
this and it rearranged all the buttons
and made it bigger.
It made it added some additional buttons
and additional for it to add additional
features added.
Added some memory buttons and then I
wired those buttons up so that we could
actually store things into memory and
then I I added the history capability so
that it remembers the calculations or
displays the calculations as we go along.
So if I did something like.
36 -, 8.
You can see that it puts that up in here
and in the calculator.
And if we say go ahead and divide that by
a four,
we get 7 and we can see that we have a
history of those and we can actually go
back to this one and get recall that 8.
We can push that into um.
Into memory and we'll see here that it
shows us what's in what's currently in
memory and we could.
Add something like that to to memory.
So now we have added to we added
something to to memory.
We can recall what is in memory etcetera.
So all of these capabilities now are are
functioning are functioning.
It's and again,
it was basically the same process that we
went through yesterday.
And the reason I wanted to do this is
because I I wanted a little bit bigger
code base to start getting into our.
Into our our brownfield coding exercises.
And so now that we have a little bit more
capability, oh,
the other thing I did here is.
Is I also encapsulated the the
calculation portion of this into a into a
separate component?
We could try to improve the architecture
slightly since it was basically embedded
in with the in with the HTML.
So I want to re-execute a a prompt that
we ran yesterday. I wanted to so can you.
Review the code days.
Or.
Clients with Evergreen software.
Practices which we did yesterday.
The word code base didn't get printed
into the prompt.
And actually it should be workspace now.
Review the workplace for compliance with
those Evergreen software practices.
Thanks for pointing it out. And again,
if you have questions on what I'm doing
right now, please raise your hand.
All right, so um,
So what this is going to do is it's
actually going to go and look at what it
understands to be.
Uh.
What it understands to be the the
Evergreen software practices.
We're not really telling it right now
what we think those should be.
We'll get to that maybe actually a little
bit later this morning.
But so right now what it's gonna do is
basically infer what it from what it
knows about this,
and then it's gonna here tell us what it
likes and doesn't like about this
implementation that we might wanna.
Take take into consideration.
So it has the typefruits proxy usage
version ranges.
There's a get ignore issue,
there's missing CICD,
there's a a a number,
a couple of security and code quality
issues.
Some type dependencies and then make some
recommendations on how to address some of
these issues.
So this will be some of the things that
we can work on in terms of approving the
code base that we already have and we can
we can incorporate any other ideas that.
You might have to do that. All right.
Any questions on just kind of catching up
to what we did yesterday? Any questions?
Yeah,
can you just show that prompt again you
used?
Sure.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
And part of what we're going to talk
That's pretty straightforward. OK, thanks.
today is how to, how to add, you know,
context into our project so that it can
make better decisions about what I'd
actually.
Should do. So for example,
what we can do is we'll be able to add
some additional context that will allow
us to to be more precise about actually
when it does these kinds of comparisons
or or evaluations.
OK, so then let's uh.
Move on.
So basically we would just want to
understand how to manipulate copilot into
successfully modifying those legacy code
bases.
Our focus is on AI assistance and
assisting AI in the in developing
software. So we want.
The main points that we want to protect,
protect those existing code bases from,
you know, you know,
inadvertent things that could AI,
you know, because AI is non-deterministic.
So we can,
we don't want to be introducing things
into the code base that we don't trust.
Also, we want to be,
we want to work towards achieving
Evergreen maturity so that we want to
essentially minimize our our maintenance
burden by trying to improve or modernize
the code base and and take advantage of
some of those Evergreen practices that
would make the application easier to
maintain.
And we want to move fast without breaking
things,
so we want to be able to accomplish more,
but we want to do it safely.
All right,
so let's talk just briefly about
Brownfielding and.
But before we do that,
I just wanted to put this on your list of
things to do. There's another.
I guess this is.
Hold on,
I got a typo there I wanted to fix.
Instead of fork,
I want to clone this AI assisted software
development repo. It's located.
It's in the at this URL.
I'll paste this into the chat.
I don't think I can do that without
stopping the presentation.
So let me.
Capture that.
And then go to the chat.
So you can go ahead and clone that.
We'll be using that. Um.
I was using this repo a little bit later,
so I'll get into discussing it,
but go ahead and if you could clone that
repo and get it ready and get it local
for you, that would be great.
H.
Alright, so moving on then.
And if you have any questions on that
cloning, just raise your hand.
So what defines a brownfield code?
It's basically an existing systems with
history constraints and some accumulated
decisions. Yes, Chris.
Just to confirm,
did you want forking or just cloning from
Cloning is gonna cloning will be fine.
the main?
OK.
I'm uh only seeing a main branch on this.
Yeah, that there should. Yeah, I.
Yeah,
I I what I'm I that was a typo on my part.
What I meant by the.
Yeah,
this is actually referring to the wrong
repo.
I was referring to our our repo when we
talk about the Brownfield branch.
So the work that we the work that we'll
be doing today will be on that ASISDASASD.
20260209 repo on the in on the Brownfield
branch.
Got it.
I'm getting access denied, John.
Yeah, me too.
You can't clone it.
It's just I don't have provisions.
OK. All right. Well,
then I'll need to add you as organizers.
I'll I'll do that as soon as I can.
You look look at the URL. Uh,
you have dot get repository.
You just need to remove that repository
from the.
Window that and try that.
Got it.
Thanks for that.
I still get access to name.
Yeah.
I was able to clone it.
We.
Has anybody able to call it?
I have it.
I I had to remove the the repository from
Yeah, yeah, it's working.
The clone worked for me.
it, but.
All right, so let me update that then.
Well, I see that it's.
We talk about an enemy.
Good.
Yeah. And Chris posted the the commands.
Thank you for that, Chris.
All right.
So going back to a brownfield code,
you know, it's it's basically there's,
you know,
it's an accumulation of decisions and
constraints and and has a history
associated with it. This code was,
you know,
shaped by real users under real deadlines
and dealing with real production.
Issues.
It's software that has survived contact
with reality, right? It's not,
it's not theoretical and it's not
something that's hasn't been used,
but something that is actually meeting
people's needs.
And it's it's a it's the best we could do
at the time with the tools and resources
that we had available.
And so, but what is not,
it's not necessarily bad code or legacy
code or a sign of of of failure or poor
engineering.
It was it's typically just what we could
do at the time and and.
As time goes on, things, things.
Things start to degrade,
even though you know even a pristine code
base will start to suffer from some of
these degrading factors.
Things like shifting in business
requirements.
If the code can't keep up with the
changing in the business,
that can that can lead to problems.
Team turnover and knowledge loss can
affect the code base.
Changes in technology as technology moves
forward that keeping the application up
to date with the with those those moving
with the technology moving forward is a
challenge.
Entropy and patchwork fixes that you know
things like quick fixes and accumulate
and architectural drift emerges as more
and more.
Demands are placed on this legacy code
and it's either missing or has outdated
card rails.
Things like test documentation and
standards that get left behind as the
code gets modified going forward.
So none of these things are intentionally
bad, but they all it just.
They just degrade the code base and cause
it to become less and less maintainable
over time to the point where many times
people decide that they should rewrite it
rather than to to modify it.
And I think that that's always a
challenge because you're trying to
reproduce existing.
Um.
You're trying to essentially recreate
existing architecture that is already
working in production.
Yeah, there's a question about the slides.
I'll I'll post the slides to the repo at
the first break.
So let's talk about what Evergreen is.
Evergreen Code asked one question.
If we wrote this today,
would it look the same as it does right
now? And if the answer is yes,
you're you're in pretty good shape.
If the answer is no,
then there's there are gaps that define
what your modernization road map would
consist of.
It's not about continuous.
It's about continuous alignment,
not perfection.
Evergreen is just a it's a it's a goal
that we're trying to obtain, but it's.
But we mean we may never actually reach a
pure Evergreen state with an existing
code base, but we can strive to do that.
So the idea is that we make small
frequent improvements and that beats out
trying to do a large rewrite.
So Evergreen is a high bar that we that
all brownfield code bases should strive
to achieve.
Before we could before a I assisted
software development it was it's very
difficult to to maintain cause it's a it
requires a a great deal of work in terms
of paying down technical debt and dealing
with the.
Those dealing with those issues that tend
to degrade code bases.
So also moving from a before AI came in,
moving from Brownfield to Evergreen was
cost prohibitive simply because of the
amount of resources that were available.
In order to be able to address that were
very expensive and and the return on that
investment really doesn't pay off in the
short term,
it only pays off in the long term.
All right.
So AI can assist us with identifying the
technical debt that we need to address,
prioritizing that technical debt in terms
of modernizing the code base so that we
get the biggest bang,
implementing the improvements.
It can help us with that.
They're also validating those
implementations.
And and documenting that progress and
we'll get into these examples of these as
we go along.
All right. Questions on this,
the Evergreen piece and why we're why
we're actually taking it on.
very well. So um
Let's talk about the essential safety
measures.
So AI accelerates development,
but it can also celebrate accelerate
mistakes.
And The thing that you should come to
realize is that it can generate an
enormous amount of code very,
very quickly.
And that poses a problem in terms of
making sure that you trust that code and
that that it's actually properly.
Reviewed and afforded actually gets put
into production.
So we need strong safety Nets before we
introduce AI into a brownfield code code
base. So these practice we'll talk about,
they reduce the risk,
they increase our confidence in the work
that we're doing and they protect those
production systems from.
Changes.
So the first thing we want to make sure
we have is backup and rollback strategies.
Basically we want to use branching
strategies that isolate AI generated
changes.
The tooling is improving a lot in terms
of this in terms it.
Takes advantage of branching when you
it'll take advantage of branching when we
create like background tasks and the like
and so it will help us in terms of that.
But we can also use our own branching
strategies to make sure that we're
working off of the main branch until we.
Get something that we think is acceptable
and merge that back in.
We wanna commit early and often to create
a natural rollback point.
So we wanna be in a position where we can
deploy the code as often as possible so
that we wanna basically we wanna be able
to isolate our changes.
In such a way that we can we can commit
them and push them into main and roll
them out into production on a very
regular basis.
We can take snapshots of critical modules
before we actually attempt to modify them.
We want to be able to ensure that we can
revert any AIS to change without any
drama.
And this is not necessarily specific to
AI,
but it's just a general good practice to
use feature flags to separate release
from deployment so that we can deploy as
often as we want,
but we release changes to the user.
Whatever they're whenever we feel
confident, they're ready.
Any questions there?
So confidence,
strong tests are the backbone of safe AI
assisted refactoring and in general
they're the backbone of any type of any
type of refactoring.
We want to make sure we have good unit
tests,
integration tests and behavioral tests
that that can validate that AI output
whenever it's created.
Our code coverage matters less than the
the signal quality.
We want to make sure that these tests
fail,
that it indicates a true problem in the
code base that we that we actually need
to address so that we want to take,
you know, in a sense.
You could in a sense you can consider the
test that you're using to validate that
the work is being done correctly,
but as being more important than the
implementation of the work itself,
because the implementation can change,
but the test really defines what the
expectation is.
That we want to maintain over time.
So this test should be protect
regressions and not just assert the happy
path.
We want to be testing you know as as
broadly as we can and then I think that
the ultimate.
Question that we want to be able to
answer at any point is that if all the
test automation passes,
how confident are you that you could
deploy it to production without looking
at it any further?
And if you have a strong test framework
that you or a test suite that you've
built around the code base.
That you can that confidence level can
increases and you can feel more
comfortable that you're ready to go to
production with anytime and you can get
to a point where you're doing basically
continuous deployment where if that test
automation passes,
you can go ahead and just automatically
deploy.
Deploy it into a production environment
and feel comfortable that that you're not
causing any major problems.
Questions. Yes, Steven.
In the third bullet point there,
coverage matters less than signal quality.
I apologize,
I'm just not familiar with the
terminology there. Signal quality.
What do you mean?
Well, it's basically,
you know differently that you want you
you want to know what the tests are
telling you is accurate.
You don't want false positives,
you don't want false negatives, right?
I was working once with a code base where
they they gave to a an offshore team.
Instructions for generating a test suite
for for this application and they they
they created over five or six months like
like a 1500 tests and.
When you however,
when you run those 1500 tests,
different tests would fail every time you
ran the tests and so you.
So we had literally no confidence that if
we ran the if we ran the the test suite
that we were gonna get back.
Actionable information that we could use
to move forward.
And there were so many tests that would
fail that it was impossible for us to
review each test in order every review
each test failure in order to determine
what the what the true signal was.
So that's really what I'm.
You're driving up at this point.
Thank you.
Sure.
I have a question. You know, let's say we,
you know, don't have a ton of unit tests.
Yep.
You know,
would it be good to use a I to create
unit tests before we do refactoring like
a I based refactoring?
Yeah,
there's no doubt that that's a good idea.
I mean, you know, you can, you know,
ask it to create a, you know, unit test.
We did a little bit of that yesterday and
we can do some more of it today,
but you definitely want to build out a
strong.
A strong test suite.
Now one of the things I've done in the
past that I that's worked out fairly well
is that you don't have, you know,
let's say you have a very large
application and you've got a huge amount
of tests that you need to write,
review and validate it's.
In order for you to be able to test the
entire application, well,
it's actually not.
You don't really have to to create all of
those tests,
you just have to take create the tests
that are going to be impacting the OR
evaluating the areas of the code that
you're actually changing.
So you really want to create a,
let's just say you're working on a module
for a back end API and you want to make a
change to a particular end point.
You just need to have good tests around
that one end point, not the entire API,
in order for you to be able to make a
modification to that end point.
Feel comfortable that you're not going to
be breaking something.
Did I answer your question, Dan?
Yeah. Yeah. Thanks.
Tom.
Hi, yeah,
I had a question about this approach as
well.
So let's say that you are developing a
lot of unit tests through AI assisted
software and then later on as you're
approaching the refactoring side of it
with AI assisted software,
will it know what to do with?
With,
let's say it identifies a large set of
code that probably isn't needed anymore,
that you had written a bunch of unit
tests for. Does it take care of?
Clean up from the whole stack or?
Yeah you can do.
Yeah you can do that if you if you've one
of the queries or prompts that you can
use that I've used in the past on legacy
code bases and I might have a a slide
address this at some point is is looking
for dead code in your code base.
Right.
And you know if you have a large large
code base trying to find that dead code
is going is going to be a challenge to do
by hand.
So you can now say I to to to review the
code base and point out anything that it
thinks is.
It is dead code and then after you've
verified that it's correct and that it is
dead code,
you can then go ahead and say OK,
I want you to remove this this code from
the code base and I'm wondering we're
we're.
Remove any tests that are associated with
this in this code as well.
The same thing would be true if you were
just deprecating an endpoint or a piece
of code or a piece of functionality.
You could say I want to not only,
you know, remove the code.
But I want to remove the the the tests
that are around that code and excuse me
and for that matter the the documentation
for it as well.
OK. Thanks.
And um.
Just going back to the concept of of
feature flags,
a feature flag is something that you put
into the code base that conditionally
executes a particular function or a
particular piece of code.
And this can do a number of things for
you.
One is it can allow you to deploy
something into production with.
With a feature turned off and users will
not be able to actually see that feature
or actively work with it even if it's.
So even if it's not fully baked and ready
to go,
you could still deploy to production with
that feature flag turned off.
And then you can conditionally turn the
feature flag on for individual users or
so that you can actually test that
particular feature in production after
it's deployed. But one of the things,
the reason I bring it up is that one of
the things that you also have to do with
a feature flag is that.
Once you've turned it,
once you turn that feature on in
production,
it's a it's a good practice to go back
and remove the feature flag.
So because it's basically never going to
be turned back off again right once it's
in production and verified.
So you need to go back and remove that
code and AI can you can use AI to go
ahead and find that feature flag and and
and gracefully remove it from the code
base.
All right. Good. Good discussion.
Thank you.
So by signal quality,
you mean like like that we're actually
testing something of value,
not just having code coverage just to
have code coverage?
Yeah, yeah, exactly right. If the code,
you know,
if you know if you're you're testing
getters and setters and things like that,
it's there's really not a lot of value in
that, right?
Because there's no real logic that you're
trying to that you're trying to verify or
if you have a piece of code that doesn't
have any external dependencies or.
And it doesn't have any branches in it.
There's a lot less value in testing that
in having rigorous testing on that code,
as if in comparison to some some piece of
code that's got a lot of complexity that
you really want to make sure is correct.
So yeah, you're correct. Yeah,
you're right.
You you want you want those tests to
provide.
Provide a a a signal that's signal that's
strong enough so that you feel confident
that you can you can release this to
production and not feel like you're
you're you're taking a an undue risk.
Yeah.
You also want to change review process.
You know,
I've heard more than one people person
say that, you know,
you can treat A I as a very eager and
very knowledgeable junior developer.
They're very,
very they can produce enormous amount of
code in a very short period of time.
But you want to make sure that everything
gets reviewed.
So you want to use a human in the loop
validation for correctness and intent
require architectural review for any
structural changes enforce standards
through.
Mentors, static analysis,
policy checks and as we get into
instruction files,
you can use those as well to enforce
standards.
And one of the things that you can do is
you can leverage AI to reduce the the the
review burden copilot.
I mean GitHub already has a feature that
if you have a pro or a pro plus pro plus
subscription that you can actually submit
a PR to a copilot or an AI code review
and it will review the PR and will add
comments to the PR for anything it finds
that that needs to be.
Addressed and it will then help you
address those those issues that it finds
to that code review.
You can then also do your own AI assisted
code reviews and I'll I'll show you a
project later where I'm.
Actually using I do I three different
models to do 3 different reviews of the
code and if two of them agree that it's a
it's good code then I then promote that
that code to be considered for.
Human evaluation.
So the idea is that you get AI to do all
the the initial AI,
the initial code review,
and then you only you only review code
that's actually passed those initial.
Uh, code review steps.
Questions here.
All right.
Well,
I'm curious to know if there's like Azure
DevOps.
There's a way to do with Azure DevOps.
It seems like mostly everything you're
teaching is on GitHub.
You know our our organizations use Azure
DevOps.
Yeah,
I I saw a message that the GitHub is,
well, yeah,
I I did find that there was a there was a
MCP tool for Azure DevOps. So there.
So you should be able to do much of what
you're doing now with that.
I haven't worked with it personally,
but no,
there's a there's a a large community of
people that are using it.
So I would expect to see support that
coming either from the third party
community or directly from Microsoft.
Which tool was that again?
It was a MCP server for Azure Devox.
You should be might be able to find it in
the extensions or in the in the gallery.
I can, I can make.
I'll make a note to do some research and
see if I can find something and if you
guys have a minute to look at it and find
something that's let us know,
that would be fine.
OK. Thanks.
Anything else I can change with you?
And the you know,
another thing is we want to keep our our
change set small, right?
So those they're the diffs are easier to
review.
And validate that they reduce the number
the potential potential for merge
conflicts and regression risk.
You can you can also limit the scope
intentionally by having a I focus on
particular files or particular areas of
the application instead of having to
review the entire code.
Code base and then those small changes
will accumulate into large improvements
over time. But as I mentioned, yeah,
I can produce a huge amount of code very
quickly. So you really have to.
If you find that it's generating a huge
amount of code,
you can actually go back and revisit.
Prompt to see if you could structure the
prompt so that it's more focused or or
break it down into sections so that you
can easily review those smaller changes
and then push them individually and test
them individually as opposed to.
Trying to grok a large change set and
trying to make sure that change set is is
something that you're that you can trust.
OK.
So that's some of the safety measures
that we can take on.
So let's talk about just how to manage
copilot. So, so copilot is powerful,
but not entirely autonomous. I mean,
you can.
You can do quite a lot without having to
intervene,
but to get the best results or effective
results,
you really have to engage in techniques
that are that are more effective,
things like.
You need to have some structure around
the work that you're doing,
some guardrails,
and you want to be clear at how you
express intent. As I said yesterday, this,
you know, this, this,
this work that we're doing is all about,
you know, expressing intent,
just we're just expressing it in.
In prompts as well in in in it,
we're expressing it as prompts in it as
well instead of syntax.
So again this is kind of treating copilot
as a developer whose output improves with
guidance.
So and we'll we can see this in a bit as
we start to to build out our own
guardrails that the the more the more
guidance that we provide the better the
outcomes that we see and the more.
Reliable those outcomes will be. So.
So basically what the process that you
use determines the quality of the AI
contributions.
So OK,
let's just understanding context and
tokens.
We got into this a little bit yesterday.
So there's a there's a context window
where Copilot can only see a limited
amount of text at once. So large files,
long conversations or or complex repos
can exceed that context.
This is probably a problem that will be
increasingly.
Less of an issue over time because every
time new versions of the models come out,
the context windows tend to increase,
which gives us more elbow room for which
we work. I'm assuming,
but we can also assume that as the
context windows improve,
the things that we ask of AI will also be
more complex and require.
Or more resources from the AI in order
for them to process them.
But in general this is something that's
gotten better over time.
So important details might fall out,
not realizing it.
And there's some techniques that we can
use to keep the keep that context focused
and keep the AI on the on.
A path that will produce output that we
were that we can utilize.
So we can do things like summaries,
instruction files,
modular prompts and work with smaller
solder sets of the code base.
So and just in terms of best practices,
we want to be explicit about what we're
trying to accomplish,
what are the constraints that we have to
that that that bound the work that we're
doing and what the success criteria.
Should be so the so you know the idea we
can if we if we create a prompt that that
tells us OK,
well this is exactly what I want to
accomplish.
These are the things that you have to to
do that you can't avoid when you do this.
And this is what it looks like for a a
successful execution.
Then a I will have a much better chance
of producing something that matches what
your expectations are.
If you provide examples,
then that that's also useful.
If you can break a large task into
smaller testable steps,
that will also improve your prompts and
to use extraction files for stable rules
and architectural boundaries,
which we'll we'll cover in in depth in
this course and in the.
Greenfield peace.
And it's always a good idea to ask a
copilot to explain its reasoning when
you're when it's important that it be
accurate.
And this is always a somewhat
enlightening exercise.
A.
To do anytime you see something that's
that either doesn't quite sit with you as
being correct,
or even something that is where you may
not quite understand what it's trying to
accomplish. You know,
for and I'll show you some examples of
sometimes in instruction.
Files will contain instructions that the
A I actually can't utilize or implement.
Questions here?
All right,
so let's take a look at some of those
techniques.
So AI tools rely heavily on that context
quality.
We can shape that context intentionally
through our work,
and this will reduce our hallucinations
on any drift and any rework.
And being able to manage the the context
is a core AI hero skill.
This is something that you always have to
kind of keep in keep in mind.
And this was a hard one.
A lesson that I learned when I was first
getting into this was I was just doing a
lot of ad hoc prompting with no,
no guardrails or guidelines that I would
get, you know,
basically every time I would do something
I would get different answers and it was
difficult to actually utilize the output
that I was.
Creating.
So we talked about the strict token
limits.
Overflow causes silent failures like
missing requirements, contradictions,
forgotten rules,
and the things that we can do to to
manage that are things like summaries,
chunking,
scoped prompts and instruction files.
We talked about what some of these
failure modes are.
And so the summaries are are useful in
that you can take a very large file that
has a lot of information that you want to
to include in the context,
and you can ask AI to summarize that file
into a smaller, shorter file.
That has the same essentially the same
meaning or same context but but with a
lot less verbiage and by doing that that
will reduce the amount of tokens that
requires for AI to process it.
I I I recall there was like a a news
flash a month or two months maybe longer
ago where open I A I was talking about
how much how much resources it was taking
them just to process thank yous that were
people were putting into the prompts
after.
Executing a prompt.
So it's basically everything that you
provide to the AI consumes part of that
context window.
So so you compress those large files.
This preserves the intent without
overwhelming the window.
You can then reuse those summaries across
across prompts.
This reduces noise and improves model
alignment.
And I'll I'll show you how to create some
of these create a summary file a little
bit later.
Questions on this, yeah.
But but you'll show us a prompt later to
do that.
Yeah, yeah.
Yes.
And so chunking means breaking a task
into smaller self-contained steps.
So you only provide the relevant portion
of the code.
You validate each chunk before moving on.
So this is also, you know,
keeps the the the context window small
because it allows you to essentially
clear the context.
Establish a a new context for the next
chunk and then go ahead and move to the
next piece and then execute the next
piece of work.
Manage as I was I showed yesterday about
that little icon that's been popping up
in the chat window that shows you how
much of the context window you've
consumed.
Staying on top of that or monitoring that,
it's a good idea about knowing when you
need to move on to a new a new session.
Scoping the prompts allows you to focus
on a single module or function.
This keeps things out of the, you know,
essentially keeps things out of the
context window.
They don't need to be there for the task
at hand,
and it helps keep our token uses more
more predictable.
Um.
One of the things I I do that I've added
to some of my instruction files is that I
ask AI to optimize its output for for use
by agents instead of humans.
A human output would be very,
very verbose and have a lot of
explanations and many different examples
that.
But if you ask it to optimize it to
reduce the the token consumption,
it will produce a much more terse.
Version of the same file that has the
same intent but accomplished but
accomplished it with a lot fewer tokens.
All right,
so so by focusing on a single module you
can say here I want to I only want to
work on the authentication module.
I want to work on the you know the API or
or I want to work on this particular file.
It will then just limit the the scope.
And allow you to focus the A I on that
the problem at hand.
One way I tend to think about the context
is that in effect the context is very is
it's very large until you provide
instructions that narrow those that that
that context down to something that's
manageable.
And then instruction files.
These provide rules that stable rules out
of the active prompt.
So what it basically what it allows you
to do is to find rules that are always
enforced. They get actually put on.
They actually get attached to every
prompt that you submit.
And this gives the ability to essentially
create simple prompts that actually have
a lot of weight behind them because
they're backed up by instructions that
give AI more details about what you're
actually meant to do.
So this provides A persistent
architectural and style guidance.
You can use it.
So you say I wanna I I want an
instruction file for C# standards and
conventions and you can use that that
that instruction file on all your C shar
projects to to make sure that they all
conform to that same.
Those same standards and conventions.
This reduces repeated tokens across
sessions.
It keeps the prompts that you need that
you're using much shorter and it has a
much more, much higher of a signal,
which means they have more.
What you're what you're providing them in
the A I is a lot more detailed in terms
of what your expectations are.
All right.
Any any questions on this building these
prompts?
But you'll give us examples for all those
kind of problems later on.
Alright.
Yes, yes,
we're gonna as we started getting AI
guide and the guide rules.
That's where we start to get into some of
the the details of this.
So what are instructions,
prompts and agents?
I've changed it from chat modes to agents
in the slides, but not in the.
Examples yet.
So that's that was a change that happened
last week creating.
So you're creating these instruction
prompts and we'll talk about creating
them themselves.
We'll also talk about what I've been
calling meta prompts or these.
These are prompts that generate other
artifacts like.
Prompts and instructions and agents so
you could you could have a prompt that
says I wanna like create me an
instruction file for for sheet for C#
standards and and conventions.
Production.
What I meant to say was create me a
prompt file that will create an
instruction file for the C# standard to
conventions and that prompt will create
one file which is a prompt file.
That prompt file will describe what the.
What you what the expectations are for
the instruction file for C# and then if
you run that prompt it will actually
create the instruction file.
This is something that is a little bit.
It takes a little bit to get your head
around in the sense that why do you need
a?
Why do you need to create a prompt file
just to create an instruction file?
But from an A I first perspective,
we want those prompts to be version
controlled and we want them to be part of
our code base.
So by creating a prompt file.
That actually documents how we created
that instruction file.
We have a better idea of what was done to
produce that instruction file,
what went into it, and if we well,
if we needed to,
we could go back to the prompt and update
the prompt and regenerate that.
Instruction file. Or even better yet,
let's just say the standards and
practices evolve over time.
You could then go back and re-execute the
prompt to regenerate the instruction file,
and that instruction file could then
include the modifications or the the
things that have changed over time.
That would affect that the instructions
for that particular technology.
So we'll talk about instruction files for
generating artifacts,
instruction files for generating code and
the like,
and also importantly is enforcing
Providence for AI assisted artifacts.
This goes along with you know what I was
just saying about the prompts.
Not only do we want to have the the the
prompt that we actually used to generate
that file captured in version controls,
but we also want to you know information
about how that prompt was executed.
When it was executed, who ran it,
what was the model that was used to
execute it?
Things like that we can capture when the
when the when the artifact is created and
and then have a essentially a a a a trail
of breadcrumbs about how all of the
artifacts that were a I generated were
created.
Questions here.
Hey John, I have a question,
but it's actually a couple slides back.
Yeah.
I didn't ask it earlier,
but you know in migrating brownfield to
Evergreen using AI if you've got code
that's not testable.
Right,
just concrete implementations all the way
through in a big monolith.
Can you talk about that a little bit?
I mean is can you, can we use,
can we use the agent to basically say, OK,
refactor all of these classes to a better
architectural structure that follows
dependency injection or something that I
can actually use to?
Uh.
Unit test these classes.
Yeah, yeah.
So now you're you're getting into an area
where it's,
it's tough to have the confidence of what
you're doing is correct, right.
Because you don't have the test to come
Right.
up, right. You know,
there's a there's a book that came out a
long time ago. It's called.
It's by Michael Feathers.
I think it's effectively working with
legacy code bases or something like that.
And there's other,
there's other places of information about
how to do this,
but the basic idea is what you want to do
is you want to find seams.
In the application where you can
encapsulate that spaghetti code and then
put test around that and so you slowly
start to basically decompose the legacy
code base into the along these seams
lines that are essentially easy places to.
To to carve out logic and put it into
separate separate separate files so they
can be independently tested.
These are all strong techniques that you
can use to help help you, you know,
break that apart.
But you know to do those initial seams
and put that initial code base,
you have to really be, you know,
be on your game in terms of reviewing the
code and making sure that it's.
That it's effective.
But yeah,
you can do it and you can you can ask it
to and you know you can actually say OK,
I want to I want to change this this
particular the function to use a
dependency injection and and I want you
to use this particular dependency
injection framework to do that.
And it will go ahead and not only modify
the code to use it depending injection,
but it would make sure that the the the
framework that you're using is installed
and working correctly as well.
Yeah.
But yeah, yeah,
what you're asking for is exactly,
I think,
what you're really wanting to use AI to
do.
Right.
I think it's the starting point for a lot
of legacy code bases really so.
Exactly. It's finding.
It's really it's finding where you can
insert those tests without having to do a
lot of code modifications to do it.
And then from once you have those tests,
you can start to to really peel the peel
2.
that onion.
And get deeper into into the logic,
extracting out new functionality into
more testable code.
Oh, cool.
Thanks for talking about that a bit.
Hey, you're welcome.
So adding guide rails,
we talked about enforcing provenance
definitions.
Instruction files are persistent rules
that guide model behaviour.
Prompts are task specific requests
defining intent.
And agents are pre-configured personas
that are optimized to perform workflows.
And these this is kind of a invert
hierarchy.
Agents kind of sit up atop of everything
and they can take advantage of prompts
and utilize instructions for what they're
attempting to try to do.
They can have commands that are
associated,
so you can invoke a not just invoke an
agent,
but invoke in a specific functionality
within that agent.
And that agent then can call out to prop
files to actually implement the the work
that you're asking here to try to do.
And all of that work could be governed by
instruction files that that are
essentially.
Static rules that you want to always have
the AI respect and enforce.
And again,
we'll have examples of all of these and
we'll utilize all of this in our work on
legacy code.
So let's talk about in creating an
instruction profile and agent files.
Why we create these files will be ensure
repeatability,
reduce our token requirements,
provide a version.
Controlled guardrails again.
So you know it's important that these
become part of our code base and a part
of our so that we have a record of what
we are actually using in terms of
guardrails for the AI generation and it
helps establish a team wide consistency.
So if I if I create a.
Instruction file that provides guidance
in terms of how the C# code should be
written. That instruction file,
if it's a part of the the project,
will be used for any and all C# code
files that get created.
And you can also then use those same
instruction files.
So if I do have AC sharp instruction file
that I want to that I have available to
me,
I can then go and prompt the AI to say
can can you review all the C# code in
this?
In this project and tell me or point out
areas where it doesn't conform to the
instructions and the instruction file and
then it will give you a a a list of
things that it would that it finds that
would need to be addressed.
All right,
so so here we have a file types.
We basically you we would put these all
in the dot GitHub folder.
You know you put the you put instructions
in the instruction folder and then you
would have have a.
A suffix of instructions dot MD so that
it recognizes it as an instruction file.
Very similar convention to the prompt
files and then for the chat chat mode
files are which are now agent files.
And then I mentioned these meta prompts,
you know,
they guide the creation of instruction
files that you can generate reusable
prompts,
help you build the construction of the
agents that basically they provide a
consistent formatting and structure and
content to the file.
So one of the ones we'll take a look at.
Uh,
early on is A and a prompt file that um.
Oh,
an instruction file that's used only when
creating prompts that create instruction
files.
So the best practices for instruction
files you define the art attack type,
you specify the required sections that
you want to see in that instruction file,
examples of or templates of of code you
the what the acceptance criteria are in
terms of when a file is generated.
What what it has to have and in order for
it to be a successful artifact and you
can require that the model restate those
constraints.
All right,
so let's just talk about enforcing
Providence. So this is again,
this is the idea of keeping track of of
how your A I code was generated.
This is of particular importance for any
any any project that that is subject to
any kind of regulatory.
Constraints where you you have to be able
to demonstrate that you know how things
were produced and that it followed a
standard practice and that you can
demonstrate that you are following that
that standard practice.
You can use these kinds of.
Provenance requirements to help provide
that kind of information for the purposes
of an audit.
So things like the AI involvement,
what what the AI actually did,
what the model that it used,
the date that it was.
That it was generated and who is the
human reviewer that actually looked at it
and and verified that was correct.
You can store this in the header of a
file or the footers of a of a text file,
or you can create what are called
sidecars, which means a a separate file.
This will be useful for like a.
Some sort of binary file or a a a file
that can't have this kind of header or
footer information in it.
We can put it in a separate file that's
then that that is then used whenever that
that particular file is invoked.
And then importantly,
we can then be able to track those in
version control so that we have a history
of what was done with those artifacts.
Yeah, cool.
All right,
so let's take an exercise here and yeah,
Can I ask you a question about that?
sure.
Yeah, um,
can you tell the model to do that?
Like to add that? Um.
Yeah, yeah,
I'm gonna show you that in in actually in
this next exercise.
OK.
All right,
so if you so the first thing I want to do
is I'm gonna copy some some files from
that AI repo that I asked you to to clone.
So let me bring that up.
I think I had it open.
So.
OK.
So this is the AI software development.
I select that.
So this file is mostly just agents
instructions.
And prompts.
That I've accumulated and and and and I
use in in projects.
So if we were to according to this
instruction file or the the this exercise
I want to copy out.
4 files and put those into our our our
project.
So the idea here is that we want to take
the chat mode instruction file,
the instruction file, instruction file,
instruction files, instructions.
The instruction prompt instructions and
then finding the prompt instructions.
So let's reveal these in the File
Explorer.
And let's I think what I'm gonna do is.
Cool.
Go back to our.
What I want to do is open up our project.
So let me move.
One of that folder.
And grab this guy again.
And what I wanna do is make sure that I'm
on the.
Correct branch.
All right.
Right. So we're on the,
I want to go into the the Brownfield
branch.
There's a couple of branches in here.
I wanted to point out there's the
Brownfield.
Baked branch.
So this is this contains actually the
result of me going through the exercises
and so you can see what the what I
created when I went through these
exercises and then the the the brownfield
one is.
Is basically only contains.
It's basically a branch off of
Fundamentals 3 and it contains the the
work that we did yesterday and the work
that I added to that after the class.
So the brownfield breaklers, brownfields.
Itself.
Alright, so we'll do that.
So we'll see here that we don't have that
file.
And we don't have.
We have a calculator web,
but we don't have much that's in the
GitHub folder,
so let me then just go out and copy these
files.
Which is I said the.
Chat mode instructions the.
Instruction instructions,
the instruction prompt instructions,
and the prompt file instructions.
We'll copy those from here into here into
the GitHub folder.
Um.
Into a new folder called instructions.
It's like I dropped one.
So let's go back.
To.
I forgot which one I didn't get.
So we got the chat mode on the
instruction file and the prompts were
missing the prompt button.
That's this guy here, so I guessed right.
And we'll have that so.
That's.
So we now see that we have these
instruction files available to us.
So let's take a look at the the first one
here will be that prompt one.
Let's take a look at that one and.
So I have a I have a a key binding that
I've created that's real helpful here
cause these are all markdown files.
So we can preview the markdown files and
I have a key binding that does two things.
It previews the file and then it opens up
into a separate window.
So if I hit that keystroke you'll see
that instruction file now.
You know,
file of it in a place of its own and I
can increase the font and do what I want
with it there.
So here we see our profile creation.
Here we can see this provenance metadata
that's at the top of it.
It has field requirements.
It's telling us that once that that it
applies to the agent mode for autonomous
file operations in chat,
what the required format is in terms of
the.
Defining the model,
what the array of required tools for that
particular prompt. So,
so then what we're doing with what we're
just to clear on this is an instruction
file,
so it is a is a list of of requirements
effectively.
And these requirements are for creating a
prompt file.
So this defines what this prompt file or
if we were asked AI to create a prompt
file,
this instruction file will tell it what
we expect to see in that file.
So it's saying it's going to have a.
A tool section here.
We're gonna have a description that
describes that particular prompt.
We'll have a prompt metadata ID output
path that defines,
and this is defining what this metadata
is.
Some common templates to use for code
generation for document generation.
This is what this metadata should include.
Include what the content structure is of
actual prompt,
what the title of the prompt is,
what the actual content is,
who's the target audience,
what the requirements are,
the technical requirements,
the output format,
what quality standards are for the output,
and with a clear statement of what this
actually needs to produce.
It has a validation checklist that the A
I should use in order to verify that what
it's created is correct.
So so the description is at the top level
and it's not in the metadata.
The model uses an explicit format.
The tools array is complete.
Et cetera. The ANA patterns.
So these are things that it shouldn't be
doing that we're calling out.
Incomplete tools, array,
vague descriptions, long mode selection,
what the file should be named.
So here it says what the domain is,
what the action, what the target is,
and then it follows with a dot.
Prompt extension asking for a kebab case
here for defining things in terms of
naming with the directory structure.
Here it's specifying that the prompts go
into a prompts folder and the output goes
into the.
The output should go of the of the prompt
should go into the instructions folder.
And then after creating it,
it wants to follow some kind of post
creation requirements which it has a link
to etcetera.
So you can see that it's a not a huge
file and what it would allowed us to
essentially do is to create a.
Defines how we actually go create any any
profile.
OK,
so questions on this on this instruction
file.
Alright,
so by putting it in the in the dot GitHub
instruction folder,
it'll it'll be treated as an an
instruction file and it will be appended
into any prompt that that actually asks
it to create a prompt file.
All right,
so now these will all be similar.
For example, if we were to look at the.
S.
Creating a new instruction file,
we'll see that it's basically some
related documentation for a I assisted
output, which we'll get into a second.
What the copilot instructions are the
instructions for the for that to to
create the file,
what the actual table of contents,
what it should see inside the file itself.
And then it will go through and talk
about when it's creating an instruction
file,
what some examples of good instruction
files are,
and it's referring to some that were
already existent that follow this pattern,
what those file instructions requirements
are,
what the front matter should look like.
What the required content structure
should be.
There's an an example of what that
instruction file should look like,
what the content guiding guidelines are.
And how it's organized.
How to go about creating the the
instruction file itself?
And what the quality standards are,
some standard patterns.
In terms of templates, et cetera.
So the reason so these these tend to
evolve over time and become more refined
as you get more experience using a I to
generate artifacts and you have you
provide more feedback to back to go back
and update this instruction.
Files to more accurately reflect what
your particular situation is or what
you're actually looking to accomplish. So.
So for example,
if you decide that that there's sections
of this that you don't really need to see
in your instruction files that it's not
adding value.
You can modify this instruction file to
say I don't want that particular section
in my instruction files anymore,
and then you could go ahead and ask AI to
apply this instruction file instruction
file to all the existing structure
instruction files and it will then go
back and then.
And remove that section or make any
updates to the instruction files that it
would that it needs that that you
specified in that instruction file.
So that the so the idea here is that
these are evolving standards or that
you're that you're refining for your own
particular use.
And I'm providing these as examples that
you can start with as opposed to having
to create them necessarily from scratch
and that this allows you to at a very
high level to define exactly.
How your governance layer is going to
look like when you start to actually ask
AI to start generating code.
So so so this is like some upfront work
that it's it's a good idea to do before
you actually get into generating any
artifacts because.
This gives AI all the information that it
needs in order to be able to produce
quality output.
So your first task would be to validate
that these these instruction files have
the information that you need and and
that you are that you want and then.
Then to then to use them in terms of
creating more project specific things,
which we'll get into in just a minute
about how do you do C# development versus
or TypeScript development versus how you,
how do you, you know,
design database schemas or anything like
that.
All right. Questions on this. Yes, buddy.
Yeah,
I was just curious we we have at at work
we have a lot of different repos and
codebase.
They all basically have the same like
most of the same standards when it comes
to like C# and like and I would want the
same thing with like I want the
instruction files and all this stuff to
be kind of standard.
Is there any good way to sync those
across or share them across repos or or
you just have to kind of manually copy
and keep them up to date?
Yeah, yeah, well,
there's a number of different ways and I
have I think in my scripts folder in the
AI.
Project.
There's some scripts for copying some of
these copilot files into a project.
That's one way of doing it, right?
Another way of doing it is.
There's a a file called copilot dot
instructions dot MD,
which is a file that's always loaded by
copilot when it's processing a prompt.
And in that file you can define where
where to find other files or instruction
files in the project, for example.
You could use a like a a a sub repo that
contains all of your generic instructions,
right?
And then you can refer to those through
this in co-piloted instruction file so
that AI is aware that they exist and and
and takes advantage of them.
But.
OK.
So that would be a that that second
solution,
that would be like a a developer
onboarding thing, right?
You'd have to make sure all your
developers have that set up on their
machines, right?
No, you would.
First off you would create a,
you would create a repo that contains all
of your generic instructions like I have
Mm.
this A I this software development one.
Then you would create a copilot
instruction file that that that points to
that sub project cause that sub project
will have a set of.
Folders in it that have it have those
instructions in it and you want to be
able to call out in that compiled
instruction file those specific those
Oh, OK.
specific files in that sub project.
So that way you now can.
You have a essentially A two-way
synchronization process that you can use
to if you make modifications externally
to the to the the common instruction
files,
you can then do just update the
subproject in all of your repos.
To pull in the new version or if and if
you make changes in any specific ones,
any specific project to that sub project
or sub repo,
you can push those changes back to the
original repo and then propagate those to
the to the rest of the organization.
Thanks.
Right.
Okie dokie.
So we looked at these instruction files,
copied them over.
The next one I want to talk about is this
AI assisted output instructions.
So let's go grab that one.
And we go here, we see that at the top.
And we'll just paste that into our
instruction file.
And we should see now that we have this
one,
this one is a a pretty substantial one.
I have a a slide deck that kind of will
walk us through what this file tries to
do.
So I call this the one instruction file
that rules them all, rules them all.
And basically what it does is ensures
Providence and logging for all AI
assisted outputs.
It defines what that metadata at the top
of the file should look like.
It documents a logging workflow that that
it that all artifacts must follow and
quality.
Gates.
So that essentially what this essentially
does is it gives us the ability to track
what what our work is doing and in in two
different two different ways.
So it protects that quote quality and
enables the audits of our existing work.
So it provides idea what the what this
providence metadata looks like.
So it specifies what it it it.
So what it does,
it requires that any instruction file
that gets created or any file actually
that's created by AI.
And and includes an indicator that it was
generated by AI,
which is kind of obvious what the model
that was used to create it,
which is a little bit sketchy right now
because it's so difficult to derive what
the username that actually ran the prompt
or ran the created that.
Or that executed the prompt that created
the file with the unique check chat
identifier is and this is basically a
made-up value that is used to identify
this particular chat session and it which
it which what it what it does is it ties
all of the conversations that you've had
with that particular.
Chat together as a group like the what
the exact prompt was that triggered that
artifact can be generated to starting and
ending time stamps.
How long it took to actually generate
that output.
It creates an AI log which is a.
A separate folder that contains a log of
the conversation that was that that
caused the artifact to be generated,
as well as a summary of that conversation
itself in case we want to.
Resume the conversation at a later date
and then we don't have that session
available to us anymore and then who or
what actually created that file.
Yeah, Chris.
Yeah,
just back before you started the metadata,
I was wondering about those instruction
files in the agent files.
I know there's an org level instructions
you can give it. Are you able to?
Add those at the org level for a GitHub
org.
Um.
You know, I'm not familiar with that.
Is that you you guys are working with a
business or enterprise license?
We will be. We will be, yeah.
Yeah, you know, I'm, I can,
I'll look into that. It would be,
that would be a great option to have and
it would be a good reason to to upgrade
to those licenses so that you could
provide that level of instructions.
OK.
standard. Yeah, yeah.
Alright.
OK. Thanks.
Sure.
So this it also defines where to place
that metadata. So it wants it's asking to,
you know,
put that YAML front mount or markdown in
similar formats in the front for binary
files and images.
It talks about creating a sidecar file.
Called artifact dot meta dot MD and then
it says don't don't use sidecars for mark
time files.
I talked about that. Um.
Chat logging workflow.
So so each chat that we execute that
causes an artifact to be created,
it will create something in the AIA
folder called AI AI logs and then in in
in a folder for the year,
a folder for the month and a folder for
the day.
And then the then the actual chat ID
that's associated with that and then it
will put into that folder the transcript
of the conversation that generated the
artifact, a summary with the objectives,
the decisions and the outcome,
which is useful for understanding the
context.
At the time and useful for
re-establishing that context in the
future if you need to,
and then with the artifacts potentially
that that were created and then it has a
requirement that we don't reuse those
chat mods between sessions.
So why all those matters? Well,
it enables auditability and trust in the
A I outputs.
This is something that we want to build
internally with our ourselves that we
actually trust those outputs.
We need to be able to communicate that
trust to to stakeholders outside of them.
Our group that we're not only using a I,
but we're using it effectively and we're
using it in in a way that is you know
conforming to our established engineering
practices and by you know defining these
this A I output.
Instruction file we can we can go a long
way towards establishing you know that
level of auditability so that if somebody
come back and somebody you know doesn't
you know either on boarding somebody or
somebody else wants to come and take a
look at what we're doing.
They have a clear set of artifacts that
they can look at that will explain that
to them.
So this also protects us against orban or
unverifiable artifacts.
So any any artifact that doesn't conform
to these particular instructions that was
a I generated will will stand out.
And it helps us to support the team
collaboration and and and any compliance
that we have. Hey buddy,
what do you what do you got?
So these are it's not.
These aren't built in features to the
copilot.
This is basically you're defining A
workflow with instruction files right to
be able to log itself and OK.
OK.
Yes.
Right.
So these are instructions that we're
That's cool.
giving that that copilot currently
doesn't support that allow us to provide
this,
allows us to create this provenance
information along with all of the
artifacts that's created and we can see
some of that.
If we go back and look at the AI
assistant instructions files,
you can see here that this provenance
information exists here in the in the
file itself and we'll see that it'll get
created into the into the files that we
actually create in the in order to define
you know additional instructions.
that we might want to follow or have AI
follow when it's running code or writing
code.
And I then that I mentioned how we've
gone through all these,
not we've looked at it all,
but I would encourage you to, you know,
to.
To take a to take a look at these these
individual instruction files and start to
understand what they do.
Another just to kind of go back into
those instruction files and take a look
at it so.
One of the things that we can do.
Oh.
With an with an instruction file.
Oh, that's not the last one. Sorry,
I'm gonna look at it some instruction
file. The chat mode one will be fine.
Uh.
I just want to.
I want to look at the markdown for this.
You can.
You can just do a control I and and bring
up the interactive,
the interactive embedded AI and just say
you know, explain.
Oh, open it.
Word.
Uh.
Wait.
Don't worry.
The validation checklist.
This is the just off the contract example.
So it's working on that.
The.
So it says here that the copilot would
treat the checklist as a deterministic
gate.
It scans the chat mode file and its path
verifies that each item against the
checklist criteria.
Concretely it would confirm the file path
matches, parse the top header.
So, so the idea here,
we're asking Copilot to explain to us how
it's going to interpret this instruction
file so that we can validate is it
actually does it,
does it interpret it the way that I
interpret it, right? Does it?
Are we on the same page about how this is
actually going to be?
Implemented and you could you know I'm
doing this as an example in a in an
instruction call we can,
but you can do this thing with any piece
of code or any artifact that you can
capture or buddy.
Have you have you had experience where
like this is a way to to I guess how I'm
trying to say I've had instruction files
that I've curated that some some models
understand that you know like follow
better than others and maybe it's just
the way it's written.
But like doing the explain if I if I
switch between different models like is
that is that like a a good way to be able
to kind of figure out and diagnose that
particular model?
Yeah, yeah.
It's a good way to dive into how the A I
is thinking about the work that you're
asking it to do. So, you know,
changing this to a different model and
having it to explain what it understands
about that model,
about that particular set of instructions
or what you're asking it to do.
I think it's a good technique.
I think I that it's something that would
be particularly if you're you know you're
seeing you're seeing you know effects
like what you're talking about where one
model doesn't seem to enforce that
instruction.
You could you could even use it you know
that explanation to help fine tune the
instruction file so that it's.
Correctly interpreted by both models.
All right. Other questions?
All right,
so we talked about the AI instruction.
We talked about the car instruction files.
So let's.
Let's create a prompt file.
So if you have access to the the repo,
you should be able to create this prompt
file on your own.
So basically we want to to understand our
our objectives,
understand that prompt structure,
practice, defining that intent.
Those constraints in the success criteria.
So we want a prompt copilot to create a
prompt file that creates an instruction
file for Evergreen software development.
And there was a sort of view of that
prompt.
We want to make sure that prompt is clear,
scoped and reusable,
includes the constraints and the success
criteria.
And it it avoids unnecessary contacts.
And one of the things that we can do,
let's see,
is right now I haven't pushed the.
I go to our projects. It's this guy.
We go to the our project here.
I have some files queued up here for it
to be pushed that contain the AI output
instructions and all of the instruction
files we created.
So what we can what I think would be a
good variation on this exercise is.
Go ahead and create the prompt to create
the prompt file that creates the
instruction file and run it without any
additional guidance and then we can then
add these files into the into the
repository.
You can pull down the instruction files.
Or you can copy them in yourself and then
rerun the prompt and clear your context
and and and then compare the results that
you get by having the instruction files
and not having the instruction files.
That that makes sense. Is that clear?
So why don't you give that a try and.
And.
So we're first going to do it ourselves,
and then we're going to do it again with
these already in there.
That was a little confusing.
Yeah, yeah. So let's do it. Just do it.
I think you can do it yourself both times.
So the first thing we're going to do is
just do it without any instruction files.
You should be looking at a essentially an
empty dot GitHub folder if you have a
have the project right now because I
haven't pushed these.
Instruction files into the Brownfield
branch yet so.
So,
so we would we want to do that the
Brownfield branch, correct?
Yes,
do it in the do it in the Brownfield
branch and because that has the, you know,
everything that you need in order to be
able to do that.
And then I will push these changes once
everybody's been able to complete the
first part of the exercise,
then I'll push in the instruction files.
You can do a refresh and then then you
can run it again.
You might want that after the first step
you want to might want to save it.
Save it out as a a separate file so that
you can regenerate it and just go from
there.
So John question what from the
instruction file? What's the sequence?
Which file shall be the first?
This is the chat mode file instruction.
Mhm.
What?
Which one we shall take as the first?
Alright,
So what we're going to be doing is we
want to create a prompt.
Let's see if I get back to the slots.
Right.
We want to create a a a a prompt that
prompts copilot to create a prompt file.
So that's part of the first part of the
Right. Mm-hmm.
prompt and that prompts.
So we want to create a prompt file and we
want that prompt file to create an
instruction file, right?
OK.
And and we want that instruction file to
be for Evergreen software development.
Right.
So what we're doing is we're creating a
profile.
That's the only thing that we that,
but that profile should contain.
Mhm.
The guidance for creating an instruction
file for Evergreen software development
and then we later we can run actually run
that prompt to actually create the
OK.
instruction file.
OK.
So it's not to go in the dot GitHub slash
prompts folder. Is that where that's?
Good, understood.
That should. Well, see,
The thing is that we haven't given that
instruction,
so it will be interesting to see what it
actually does.
Well, it's asking.
It's asking me where to put it.
All right,
well then you put it anywhere you want,
but dot the dot GitHub instruction folder
is where it should live.
OK,
just got that GitHub or or so it's
instructions. OK,
I thought this is a prompt file,
so that's why I was wondering if it would
be a prompts.
Oh yeah, you're right.
It should go in the prompt folder.
That's my mistake.
Bob created a pretty extensive
obstruction file from.
We just need to compare.
Yeah, you would. It'll, you know,
it's going to create the instruction file.
It's not going to give up on it,
but we're looking to see how well that
conforms to what the if we add the
additional instruction files or how to
create a prop file would look like, right?
So it'll be there and it's just inferring
this from what it knows.
Yeah.
So it's gonna be getting some of its
information. I mean, to be, you know,
to be perfectly honest,
I didn't write these core instruction
files by hand. I had I had AI help me.
Build those instruction files so it's it
already knows intrinsically about how an
instruction file might look,
but it doesn't have like the Providence
Yeah.
pieces in it,
and it doesn't have some of the other
details that might be in this file that.
So.
All right,
so it's so we we should expect to see
some significant differences between what
gets generated and also will depend upon
what model that we use to do the
generation.
All right,
who who's not done creating the prompt
file?
If you raise and leave,
raise your hand and leave it up.
That would be good.
Everybody's done then.
All right,
so let me get those instruction files to
you.
First I need to commit this gitignore
file.
Oh, looks like I'm getting myself.
Oh, merge changes.
All right,
so I'm just going to resolve this merge
conflict.
We gotta save notes.
And.
Stage it.
And then I'll unstash the.
And go ahead and stage these and commit
them.
And.
They should now be available for you to
pull.
So go ahead and pull it and then go ahead
and.
Go ahead and try that exercise again.
And when you're finished,
go ahead and raise your hand.
That way I know when everybody's done
with this exercise.
John,
when you did that that push that those
commits it's looked like it auto
generated your comments is that is that
right or?
Yes,
that's what this little button here does.
If you have a change,
you can generate a commit message and AI
will try to determine from those files
that you have have got.
As you modify what they what you actually
change and try to generate try to create
a commit message that matches that.
I find that to be mostly reliable.
Sometimes though it will say refactored X
in order to accomplish Y or something
like that and or a generic message you
know just made some changes.
Generic message that actually isn't
specific. When I find that happening,
I typically try to break down the the
commit into smaller pieces and then I can
get a better idea about.
About the contents of the of the PR and
another way and one way to do that is to
only stage the things that you want to
generate a commit message for and it will
only look at those files and not the
entire set of changes that you've made.
OK, by the way,
we should open up a new chat window when
All right.
we do the prompt again, right?
Yes, you should. You want to clear your.
You want to clear your contacts,
your contacts so that it's not done.
Nothing's bleeding over from the first
time that you ran it.
All right.
So the last part of this exercise will be
to use AI to compare the two files and
report the significant differences.
So you you talked about the regulatory
aspect,
you know to keep like a chain of chain of
custody like you know history is is that
actually required now like cause one of
the products I work on is FDA cleared,
you know, so we have a 510K.
Is that that's something that's like in
like in place or that's going to come?
Mm.
Do you have any ideas about that?
Well.
The FDA has some.
Some preliminary guidance on AI generated
software.
That that guidance is not finalized and
it doesn't have expectations to this
specific level of detail,
so it's not requiring this kind of
providence per se.
But what it does require is that you have
a process that that you follow and and
that you can demonstrate that you follow
that allows you to explain.
How what was generated and your your
understanding of how that was done.
So in a sense you have to treat it like
any other software development process,
whether it's a human or a.
Organization exactly how you produce this
output,
and that's the I think the purpose for
wanting to have this kind of providence.
And if you, you know,
if you decide you don't need it,
you certainly can remove it from the
instructions and it would not be
generated.
But I find it helpful to have that
conversation history.
I find it helpful to be able to resume to
a particular point in time,
even on a different machine. You know,
having that conversation and that session
file helps you do that.
And um.
And having that header information,
I also think is useful to to have.
Anybody still working on this part?
Anybody.
So it's anybody see significant
differences between the two versions of
the file?
Yes, not a bit.
Oh.
All right. So,
so those significant differences, what,
what did they look like?
Oh, it is a a long list.
I mean the mode declaration model
specification,
the fact that it creates logs.
Interesting that the copilot told me to
use the.
The new format instructions when I want
to generate instructions via AI and use
the original one if I want to do it
manually, just as a checklist to follow.
Yeah, that's an interesting point.
That was something else that that,
you know,
I started off doing exactly what we did
in the first exercise and and and all of
my instructions files were very verbose
and very cleaned,
a great deal of information.
And I started to run into issues with
context windows and that's where I've
gone back and you know,
modified the A I output to specifically
require that that that the output be
targeted at an A I agent and it's.
And and it needs to optimize for to
minimize token consumption and you get a
much much more terse version of the same
file.
You know having a a human readable and a
human targeted instruction file.
Is only useful if it's actually going to
be a part of your manual code writing
OK.
process, right? Yeah,
but I don't think that you necessarily
need to have all of that metadata for
your.
Manual code process necessarily,
but you know you can you can make a a
Mm.
decision about that.
But I wouldn't put them in the the GitHub
instruction folders,
I would put them in the docs folder as or
someplace outside of it so it doesn't get.
Treated as an instruction file for for
your A I generated content because
there's right you you could leave it
there if you wanted to put you know
Right.
Yeah, that makes sense.
explicit instructions inside of the file
that not use it for a I generated content.
But it seems not like not a good idea to
put it in that place if you don't intend
it to be used by AI.
That makes sense.
Anybody have a?
Anybody have a a comment or?
A question about how their exercise went.
OK.
My recommendation was different.
It said to merge some of the core
principles from the original document
with the new document.
Oh, really?
So what did it find in the original
document that it liked?
Well,
the core principles it said there that
the including the core principles section
from the promptus conceptual foundation.
OK, I see what I'm saying. Yeah,
that might that that might not be a bad
idea, right? Because I mean,
we're we're creating an instruction file
that's all about Evergreen software
development.
So having the core principles defined in
that file might actually be worthwhile.
And it gave me a nice table that I posted
in the chat.
Oh, let me take a look at that.
Oh, Alex, interesting.
So this is kind of demonstrating a bit of
the non-deterministic nature of it, right?
We don't provide guidance where the
output that we get can definitely vary.
Using essentially the same prompt,
you get a completely or very
significantly different output based on
the instruction files that we give it.
And that's the reason that we want to use
those instruction files because we want
something that's more.
Reproducible,
something that is more dependable so that
we can we can rely on the A I generated
code more and and having to scrutinize it
less because we've given it the guidance
that it needs in order for it to be.
Uh, to produce things that we expect.
All right, so I think that was successful.
Let's move on then to creating the
instruction file.
So now that we have a a prompt,
we can go ahead and submit that that
prompt that we created and and create an
instruction file from that prompt.
So Al's got something else.
You got a different table.
And so and it's pointing out things that
it's missing, right?
All right, so this exercise created.
So we need to run the instruction file,
run the prompt to generate this
instruction file,
and we should be able to review that
instruction file and and and see that it
conforms to the.
To the instructions that we've the core
instructions that we've already provided.
Right, let me find the.
So we do it with the current.
Yeah, yeah.
I don't think we want to go back.
And.
So what's the prompt?
Create a Evergreen instructions file.
Well, you created the prompt.
Should be in your prompts folder now,
right?
OK.
So the prompt will be something like, uh,
you know, submit this prompt file.
So John,
we're creating the instruction files from
the prompt file we created basically.
That's correct.
We just want to submit that prompt file.
Yeah.
That takes a minute, but it worked out.
Good.
All right, so um.
Who's finished? Who's finished with that?
Anybody see any anything anything
interesting in the in the instruction
file that was created?
Mine's still working. Sorry.
Oh, sorry.
I'm amazed at what it created.
Architectural context. It's it's crazy.
Yeah, I mean,
it's one of the slides coming up is that
Yeah.
that inference is your friend, right?
Here we're giving it a, you know,
a fairly we started off with a fairly
basic prop that's like creating a prop
file.
We didn't say what was gonna be in that
profile other than what a profile should
contain,
and then it creates a a a a detailed.
Prompt file from those basic instructions
and infers that what the content should
be based on what it knows from its vast
knowledge that's embedded in the model.
And the same thing is true for the
instruction file. It doesn't, you know.
The profile tells it to create a a
instruction file for Evergreen software
development,
and it may contain some information about
what Evergreen software is,
but in terms of creating the detailed
instructions,
those are also inferred as well.
So it's, you know,
from that prompt first perspective,
Mhm.
the idea is let's create the prompt,
let's create the content.
It's easier to delete content than it is
to write content. You know,
if we were to sit down and say I wanted
to write this instruction file by hand.
You would first have to figure out what
needed to be in the instruction file,
which is, you know,
some effort on your own.
And then you'd have to, you know,
come up with verbiage and then you would
have to, you know, continually review,
review and revise it in order to get
something that that would be acceptable.
Here we can start off with something that
is.
You know,
pretty close to what we actually think we
want. And then we can edit it to become,
you know,
precise what we precisely what we want.
If there is something that we think that
we need to change.
And there's two places that we could make
that change.
We could change the instruction file
directly.
Or we could go to the prompt that we used
to create the instruction file and we
could tweak that so that it produces
something that is more suitable to what
we want.
And the benefit of I think the second
approach or like modifying the prompt
file is that it permits that.
Change into into into this into source
control along with the prompt itself and
as well and then then we also then we use
it to generate the instruction file.
It gets updated as well and we preserve
those changes.
So and if you think about what we use to
create the prompt file,
it was a very straightforward prompt.
Which is just create a prompt that
creates an instruction file for this
particular purpose and it this is just as
a as a as a practice creating the prompt
file to create the instruction file is I
think.
A a a pretty good practice because if you
think about the provenance that would go
into the instruction file,
if we were to do it without a without a
Yes.
specific profile,
it would just be create an instruction
file for.
Evergreen software development and that
would be the prompt,
whereas the we now have a prompt file
that contains much more detail about what
we want that that instruction file to
contain and that becomes a part of the
record.
All right, great.
So this takes us up to the break.
So I'll see you guys in an hour.
If you have any questions,
I'll join the chat a little early and we
can answer those questions there and I'll
I'll see you guys in an hour.
Thanks, John.
You're welcome.
Remember to join a new chat.
Thanks.
Thank you.
We have a new, a new, a new call.
It's in in the afternoon. It's a new call.